Eva vom Baur Hansl Papers
Eva vom Baur Hansl Papers
1918-1968
Hansl, Eva vB. (Eva vom Baur).
11 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, journalist, radio producer, and lecturer (1899-1978). Collection includes biographical material, correspondence, radio broadcasts files, speeches, and writings. Bulk relates to the radio programs for which Hansl was program supervisor (1939-1940): Women in the making of America, broadcast in cooperation with the WPA's Federal Theatre Radio Division, and Gallant American women, with the support of the U.S. Office of Education. Hansl later produced Womanpower (1943-1944), in cooperation with the War Manpower Commission.
149032
Biographical History
Eva Elise vom Baur Hansl, woman's editor and pioneer in women's radio broadcasting, was born to Elise Urchs and Carl Max vom Baur on 29 Jan 1889 in New York City, the youngest of five daughters and a son. She attended the New York Collegiate Institute and after graduating from Barnard College in 1909 became a member of the Intercollegiate Bureau of Occupations, one of the earliest organizations concerned with employment for women. From 1911-1916 she reported the progress of the early feminist movement for the New York Tribune and the New York Evening Sun; at the latter she was editor of the women's page from 1912-1916. In 1915-1916 she directed a course of public lectures at New York University on vocations for women, and from 1916-1918 she organized the League for Women's Vocational Opportunities. She was an associate editor of Parents magazine and organized play-schools and parents' study groups in Princeton and Summit, New Jersey and in Greenwich, Connecticut.
In 1916 she married Raleigh Hansl, from whom she was later divorced. When her two children, Barbara and Raleigh, were grown, she returned to journalism with the Education Department of the New York Times. Her efforts on behalf of the education and employment of women continued for the next four decades. In 1936 she founded Trend-File, a reference service on women's interests and activities, which she maintained for many years. Her long interest in women's activities led to broadcasting when she supervised the research, promotion, and production of three network radio series: "Women in the Making of America" and "Gallant American Women"for NBC, in cooperation with the U.S. Office of Education (1939-1940), and "Womanpower," for CBS in cooperation with the War Manpower Commission (1942-1943).
In 1941 Hansl left New York City to work in Washington with the War Manpower Commission, but after that returned to New York City which remained her home for the rest of her life. From 1947-1950 she was a member of the committee of the World Center for Women's Archives, Inc. in New York City. She lectured at New York University and Columbia University, and wrote several books including Minute sketches of great composers (1931), Artists in music today (1933), Trends in part-time employment of college trained women (1949), and many articles in popular periodicals.
Eva vB. Hansl died on 11 Apr 1978.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Eva vom Baur Hansl Papers comprise biographical material, correspondence, radio broadcasts files, speeches, and writings, with one box of miscellaneous material. The papers date from 1918-1968 but her years in radio broadcasting are the most heavily represented. There is relatively little material from her early career as newspaper women's page editor. Her lifelong interest in women's vocational opportunities and guidance is reflected in the correspondence, speeches, and writings.
The collection begins with a small amount of Biographical material. Correspondence covers 45 years (1923-1968).
Radio files contains indexes to all three of Hansl's radio programs, production files, and promotional material. Research files contains research material for the radio programs; topcs include freedom of speech, suffrage, women explorers, businesswomen, and more. The collection also includes Scripts and Radio Broadcast Files for more than 40 episodes.
Speeches span Hansl's entire career (1921-1968) and include also Hansl's notes. Other Writings include articles, book reviews, book outlines, and a small amount of verse, as well as a few items written by others.
Legal and financial contains copyright and insurance information, and a small amount of Memorabilia completes the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Radio files are arranged alphabetically. Research files are in chronological order according to broadcast date of the episode for which the material was gathered. Scripts and Broadcast files are also in broadcast date order. Speeches and writings are in no particular order.
Related Material
See also the
Eva vom Baur Hansl Collection of Women's Vocational Materials
, an extensive and comprehensive collection of research material and publications on women and employment, including topics such as conferences, continuing education, general education, history, home and family issues, international and foreign women, women during the war years, and "womanpower" (as analogous to "manpower").
Subject and Genre Headings
Journalism; Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Women Authors; Hansl, Eva vB. (Eva vom Baur) -- Archives.; Federal Theatre Project (U.S.); United States. -- Office of Education.; United States. -- War Manpower Commission.; United States. -- Works Progress Administration.; Gallant American women (Radio program); Womanpower (Radio program); Women in the making of America (Radio program); Adult education -- United States.; Documentary radio programs.; Feminism -- Archival resources.; Feminists -- United States.; German Americans.; Housewives -- United States.; Professional education of women.; Radio authorship.; Radio programs.; Radio producers and directors -- United States.; Radio scripts -- Specimens.; Women -- Biography.; Women -- Education.; Women -- Education (Higher); Women -- Employment.; Women -- History -- Archival resources.; Women -- Intellectual life.; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Women in politics.; Women -- Social conditions.; Women -- Vocational education.; Women -- United States.; Women in radio broadcasting.; Women authors, American.; Women in the mass media industry.; Women journalists -- United States.; Women's mass media.; Women's rights -- United States.; Women's studies -- Archival resources.; Bibliographies.; Biographies.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Pamphlets.; Radio scripts.; Speeches (documents); Surveys (documents); Authors.; Feminists.; Journalists.; Lecturers.; Radio producers and directors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Jan 1923 - Jun 1940, 25 folders (Box 1)
  - Jul 1940 - Jun 1957, 23 folders (Box 2)
  - Jul 1957 - Dec 1961, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - 1962-1968, 15 folders (Box 4)
  - Undated (Box 4)
  - No year (Box 4)
  - Fragments (Box 4)
- Radio files
  - Indexes
    - Master list (Box 4)
    - "Women in the Making of America" series (Box 4)
    - "Gallant American Women" series, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - "Womanpower" series, 1942-1943 (Box 4)
  - Production files
    - Audition script (Box 5)
    - Office of war information, 1942; printed material (Box 5)
    - Consultants (Box 5)
    - Contracts and agreements (Box 5)
    - Copyright (Box 5)
    - Outlines (Box 5)
    - Clippings about the series (Box 5)
    - Memoranda (Box 5)
  - Promotional material
    - Book outline (Box 5)
    - Posters (Box 5)
    - Promotion lists (Box 5)
    - Publicity releases (Box 5)
    - Name lists (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Research files
  - Bibliographies (Box 5)
  - Synopses on women (Box 5)
  - Preliminary research notes for "Gallant American Women' (Box 5)
  - Biographies, historical, general; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Biographies, historical, specific people
    - A (Box 5)
    - B-Z, 10 folders (Box 6)
  - Freedom of Speech and Assembly, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Freedom of Education, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Women in politics and government, including suffrage, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Women as homemakers (Box 7)
  - Agriculture (Box 7)
  - Women in industry, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Women in the arts (Box 8)
  - Women in social welfare (Box 8)
  - Peace (Box 8)
  - Women on the land (Box 9)
  - Women the providers (Box 9)
  - Refugee women (Box 9)
  - Suffrage (Box 9)
  - Law, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Seafaring women, 2 folders (Box 9, 10)
  - Women of learning (Box 10)
  - Women as teachers (Box 10)
  - Women explorers (Box 10)
  - Women of letters (Box 10)
  - Mothers of great Americans (Box 10)
  - Fashions in sentiment (Box 10)
  - Bronze Tablet (Box 11)
  - Ladies in journalism (Box 11)
  - Women of the opera (Box 11)
  - Women in medicine (Box 11)
  - Women in fashion (Box 11)
  - Nursing, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Women in science (Box 12)
  - Theatre, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Children First (Box 12)
  - Women in Aviation (Box 12)
  - The American home (Box 12)
  - Through Space and Time (Box 13)
  - Sports (Box 13)
  - Businesswomen, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Libraries (Box 14)
  - Dance (Box 14)
  - Gallant American Women
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 14)
    - Quick reference file for scripts, A-M (Box 14)
    - Quick reference file for scripts, N-Z (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous notes, A-Z, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Colonial period, 1607-1775 (Box 15)
    - Revolution and after, 1775-1800 (Box 15)
    - Young republic, 1800-1865 (Box 15)
    - Post Civil War, 1865-1900 (Box 16)
    - Modern times, 1900-1940 (Box 16)
- Scripts
  - Cavalcade of American Women, May 19, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Freedom of Worship, May 26, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Freedom of Assembly, June 2 1939 (Box 16)
  - Freedom of Speech, June 9, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Freedom of Education, June 16, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Freedom of Citizenship, June 23, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in Politics & Government, June 30, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women as Homemakers, July 7, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in Agriculture, July 14, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in Industry, July 21, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in Arts and Crafts, July 28, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in Social Welfare, Aug. 4, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women for Peace, Aug. 11, 1939 (Box 16)
  - These Freedoms, Oct. 31, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women for Peace, Nov. 7, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women on the Land, Nov. 14, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women the Providers, Nov. 21, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Refugee Women, Nov. 18, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women are People, Dec. 5, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Laws and the Women, Dec. 12, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women in the Law, Dec. 19, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women of the Sea, Dec. 26, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Women of Learning, Jan. 2, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Women as Teachers, Jan. 9, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Women Explorers, Jan. 16, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Women of Letters, Jan. 13, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Mothers of Great Americans, Feb. 6, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Fashions in Sentiment, Feb. 13, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Women who Saved Mount Vernon, Feb. 20, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Ladies of the Press, Feb. 27, 1940 (Box 16)
  - Women of the Opera, Mar. 5, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Medicine, Mar. 12, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Fashion, Mar. 19, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Nursing, April 2, 1940 (Box 17)
  - From Tavern to Tearoom, April 9, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Science, April 16, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Behind the Footlights (Box 17)
  - Children First, April 30, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women with Wings [aviation], May 7, 1940 (Box 17)
  - The American Home, May 13, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Politics and Government, May 20, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Through Space and Time, May 27, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Wives of Great Americans, June 3, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Sports, June 10, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Commerce and Trade, June 17, 1940 (Box 17)
  - On With the Dance, July 1, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Women in Government Arms Plants / Women in Washington Government Offices, Aug 2, 1942; Aug 9, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women in the Naval Reserve / Women in Aircraft Production, Aug 16, 1942; Aug 23, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women who Feed War Workers / Women in the Labor Movement, Aug 30, 1942; Sept 6, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Report to the Nation, Feb 17, 1942 (Box 17)
  - "General", Jun 7, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women on the Land, Jun 14, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women in Government Plants / Women in the War Industries, undated (Box 17)
  - Womanpower / Protection of Workers' Children, Jul 19, 1942; Jul 26, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women in Science / Women in the U.S. Employment Service, Sept 13, 1942; Sept 20, 1942 (Box 17)
  - Women in Army Ammunitions / Womanpower in Air Power / Women in Recreation for War Workers, undated (Box 17)
  - Women in Public Health Nursing / Women Who Build Ships [transportation], undated; includes interview (Box 17)
  - [war efforts] / [food purchasing] / interviews with D. Stratton and M.E. Switzer (Box 17)
- Radio Broadcast Files
  - Cavalcade of American Women, May 19, 1939 (Box 17)
  - Freedom of Worship, May 26, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Freedom of Assembly, June 2 1939 (Box 18)
  - Freedom of Speech, June 9, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Freedom of Education, June 16, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Freedom at Citizenship, June 23, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women in Politics & Government, June 30, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women as Homemakers, July 7, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women in Agriculture, July 14, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women in Industry, July 21, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women in the Arts, July 28, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women in Social Welfare, Aug. 4, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women for Peace, Aug. 11, 1939 (Box 18)
  - These Freedoms, Oct. 31, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women for Peace, Nov. 7, 1939 (Box 18)
  - Women on the Land, Nov. 14, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Women the Providers, Nov. 21, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Refugee Women, Nov. 18, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Women are People, Dec. 5, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Laws and the Women, Dec. 12, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Women in the Law, Dec. 19, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Seafaring Women, Dec. 26, 1939 (Box 19)
  - Women of Learning, Jan. 2, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women as Teachers, Jan. 9, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women Explorers, Jan. 16, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women of Letters, Jan. 13, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Mothers of Great Americans, Feb. 6, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Fashions in Sentiment, Feb. 13, 1940 (Box 19)
  - The Bronze Tablet, Feb. 20, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Ladies of the Press, Feb. 27, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women of the Opera, Mar. 5, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Medicine, Mar. 12, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Fashion, Mar. 19, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Nursing, April 2, 1940 (Box 19)
  - From Tavern to Tearoom, April 9, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Science, April 16, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Behind the Footlights (Box 19)
  - Children First, April 30, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Aviation, May 7, 1940 (Box 19)
  - The American Home, May 13, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Women in Politics and Government, May 20, 1940 (Box 19)
  - Through Space and Time, May 27, 1940 (Box 20)
  - Wives of Great Americans, June 3, 1940 (Box 20)
  - Women in Sports, June 10, 1940 (Box 20)
  - Women in Commerce and Trade, June 17, 1940 (Box 20)
  - Librarians and Curators, June 24, 1940 (Box 20)
  - On With the Dance, July 1, 1940 (Box 20)
  - Transcripts of two interviews with Eva vB Hansl, on "Let's Talk it Over", 1928 (Box 20)
- Speeches
  - The American woman's heritage / Contribution of the educated woman to the life of today and tomorrow / Education for parenthood, 1947; 1927,; 1923 (Box 20)
  - Life careers for women, 1958 (Box 20)
  - Making the most of vacations / Parenthood and colleges, undated; 1921 (Box 20)
  - Shortages / Utilization of womanpower, 1956; 1952 (Box 20)
  - What 1937 has meant to women of the USA / Wives, mothers and education, 1927 (Box 20)
  - Perspective on American women from colonial to modern times, 1968 (Box 20)
  - The woman mess, 1964 (Box 20)
  - Womanpower / Women as family labor / Women on the 1938 horizon, 1943; 1944, (Box 20)
  - On woman's progress, 1953 (Box 20)
  - Notes for untitled speeches, 1921-1936; undated; 2 folders (Box 20)
- Writings
  - Article outlines (Box 20)
  - List of E. vB. Hansl's published writings, post-1962 (Box 20)
  - Articles, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Book reviews (Box 21)
  - Notes on interviews with Charles and Mary Beard, Harriet Stanton Blatch, Sophie Lewis Drinker (Box 21)
  - Reminiscences - "Jottings on Journalism", 1919 (Box 21)
  - Verse (Box 21)
  - Fragments (Box 21)
  - Miscellany
    - Book outline (Box 21)
    - Sketches of composers' early lives (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Of others
    - Beard (Box 21)
    - Catt, Carrie Chapman (Box 21)
    - Hatcher (Box 21)
- Legal and financial
  - Copyright and insurance (Box 21)
- Memorabilia
  - 1918-1960, undated (Box 21)